If I want to practice for the giving up
of sensuality, how do I discern the
difference between those sense objects
that I have to give up and the ones that
are fine? Well,
you don't it's not even the sense
objects that you have to give up. Um it's
Um it's
your engagement with them
needs to be
controlled or restrained. And
And
what determines that is
the passion behind that engagement.
So, because
because
sense objects will present themselves
whether you like it or not.
Even the let's say
the bad ones that have the potential
to induce passion,
even if you live completely isolated
from the whole world,
as the Buddha said, the sixth sense
space is
uh is the mind.
That one's always with you, which means
at any point
the bad sense objects can still show up. Um
Um
so you can't give it up in that sense uh
except by trying to control the
circumstances, which will always fail
sooner or later, and that's never going
to lead to
any uh stable kind of freedom.
But if you understand it's about the
engagement, then you realize, well,
then you realize, well,
what's the coarsest type of engagement
I can have?
It's physical engagement.
So, that's why it starts with the
precepts. Uh you will still encounter
Uh you will still encounter
pretty much the same sense objects
throughout your life.
It's inevitable
to some extent.
But how far you engage with them,
you start to put a limit on that. And
what that's what the precepts do.
Uh
if you have done that,
then you can start to see how you engage
with sense objects even on the mental
level. Which is then the practice of sense
Which is then the practice of sense
restraint.
Uh as it's described, grasping signs and
features of sights
of sights
in such a way that or sounds, smells,
tastes, and touches in such a way
that uh
lust or aversion
arise. That's what you abstain from. Like
That's what you abstain from. Like
grasping signs and features in such a
way. And that's all now on the level of your
And that's all now on the level of your
mind.
How you kind of
uh give your or or or
uh direct your attention
at these objects that come up.
Because see, it's it's a it's a even
though for people who haven't kept the precepts
for people who haven't kept the precepts
sufficiently, it doesn't seem that way.
Uh there is a difference between
something just kind of appearing even mentally,
just kind of appearing even mentally,
and then you choosing to kind of engage
it engage with it and and sort of
extract the pleasure from it.
Cuz you always have that
difference, which is why you feel the
kind of
um
that kind of like dissonance or
dissatisfaction when
uh you start keeping the precepts and
you haven't been doing it before. You
have this In a way, you have the same
object. Uh that kind of present to your senses,
Uh that kind of present to your senses,
but you're not
extracting enough from it. You're not
kind of
uh um
going far enough.
Whatever arbitrary threshold you're used
to in your engagement with it.
Um so
it's that engagement of like
for example,
uh um
celibacy. Like for a
Like for a
average person who's not used to it,
um
simply coming across
uh attractive people
and not in engaging in in or in trying
to initiate any kind of
uh sexual interactions and just not
making efforts in it in in that
direction, that's already going to kind of leave
that's already going to kind of leave
them feeling that that sort of void
of not getting the amount of engagement
that they're used to.
Uh which already shows them like, well,
technically I'm still seeing
uh
all the things that I would have engaged
with before, but just I'm not engaging
with it enough.
Um so
when you um
expand that same principle to the mental
level, you realize the same applies. Like
you realize the same applies. Like
things appear
vaguely, sort of like a like a
sort of like a blurry
uh
perception of some sensual thing.
And then
your mind wants to sort of latch onto it
and dwell on it more.
And then you don't allow that. But you
don't in the same way as like a like a
person who would be present in the room,
but you know that you're celibate,
you're not going to
uh make any efforts to to connect with
them on a on a sexual level.
on a on a sexual level.
Um you
in the same way, you're not going to
make any effort to further expand
this sensual perception that arose just
in a mental level.
And then even if it stays there for
days, nothing unwholesome will have happened
nothing unwholesome will have happened
unless you made that choice of expanding
on it,
focusing on it, kind of like I said,
trying to extract more from it.
And you will feel that same sort of like
um
like void, like you're not kind of
getting what you expect from it, even
though it's there.
Sort of floating around ambiguously.
Um so
that's exactly then how you start to
realize it's not really the it's not the
sense objects.
It never was the sense objects.
It's that engagement
that engagement
that you that you
that it really is what your mind craves
for. It's basically like um
It's basically like um
this kind of secondary distraction
that blurs
that painful void
that you feel when you see something
attractive. So that's why for example, when you
So that's why for example, when you
have are giving in to something
uh like
something you desire
and then all of a sudden it's it's not
that it's taken away completely,
but you're just kind of
temporarily interrupted in your
engagement, you already feel the pain.
you already feel the pain.
Even though you didn't lose it,
which is what most people would think
like, oh you you feel pain because I
lost it externally, like
like if I if I still had it,
if the person hadn't died or whatever,
like I I wouldn't be suffering, but then
you realize
yes, but that's really secondary. It's
never about the person or or about the
object. It's
It's
that engagement allows you
a kind of like a, uh,
temporary escape
from the pain
that the desirable thing exerts simply
due to its presence.
And why is that the case? Well, that's
just how existence is. As the Buddha
said, the the sense uh organs themselves
are painful.
The six six sense bases.
Um so, it's like that actually like that
simile of the of the leper.
Um
like burning his wounds
burning his wounds
in the charcoal pit
provides him this kind of temporary
relief from the itching of his wounds
from the itching of his wounds
while at the same time making it worse.
Increasing his dependence on needing to
like see
both in the terms that the leprosy gets
worse and also in the sense that he's going to
and also in the sense that he's going to
be even less able
to to put up with the itch
when it arises on its own without going
to the charcoal pit.
So, um that's the dependence on on sen-
sensuality. Which yes, uh uh uh
Which yes, uh uh uh
it has something to do with the objects.
It's not completely [snorts] separate
from it cuz nobody would
um
seek that gratification from something
that's not pleasant.
It has to be pleasant first.
That's why the Buddha defined the the
five, uh, strings of sensuality as
things that are agreeable.
Enticing. Otherwise, it could not be uh a means
Otherwise, it could not be uh a means
for that temporary distraction.
It's not going to captivate you enough
for you to start ignoring
the painful desire that's underneath.
So, it's almost like kind of
um
it it it
it's not that the the goes away
which is why you need to keep escalating
your engagement.
It's really just It allows you to sort
of
not have to think about it.
Not have to think about
that underlying pain of craving that's
actually driving your engagement.
Because the engagement comes with all
this pleasure and all these details for
you to focus on.
>> So, in in other words, the whole
realm of sensuality is just uh
maybe the closest form of
distraction. >> Yeah, it was a cover-up, yeah.
>> Yeah, it was a cover-up, yeah.
So, it's a it's a means for you to
well, ignore the the pain that comes
with the sensual desire itself
while increasing the the desire
through ignoring it.
Cuz again, it's not that sometimes
people think if I
give in enough
and I get enough experience
with sensuality
then naturally I won't be as interested
in it
as before.
And that's completely based on their
misconception that
sensuality is in the objects.
Cuz yes, if you eat the same food for
10 years, you're going to be bored.
But that has absolutely nothing to do
with that mechanism of when you see something
that mechanism of when you see something
that is attractive.
So, that food is not going to be
attractive when you've been eating it
after 10 years, but that that doesn't
count then.
When you find something that is actually
attractive to you,
can you like are you then pressured
immediately to engage with it further,
to latch on to its details?
Because if you are, then that's what
sensuality is.
That's what the sensual desire is. So then,
So then,
if you
like are honest with yourself, you'll
see that never stops. Like you can
scratch to the point where
very few things that you can
encounter on a
regular enough basis are attractive.
But something will still be attractive
to you.
And it just gets more and more extreme,
more and more refined.
Which really means you're just confining
yourself further and further.
Narrowing down your avenue of escape.
So that's why even for people who were
not going to practice
and try to free their minds from
craving, it was still better for them to contain
it was still better for them to contain
their sensual desires as much as
possible. Cuz then you factually have more things
Cuz then you factually have more things
to to even even wrongly, but like to to
kind of um
appease that itch.
Whereas the more you give into it,
the narrower and narrower
both things become. Like your ability to
get the sensual verification and your
ability to escape from sensuality
altogether.
So that's why there's no benefit
whatsoever if your aim is to practice to give in.
if your aim is to practice to give in.
Because yeah, while you might
become more familiar with certain things
and stop craving them,
that habit
of something
pressuring you towards it towards
engagement is going to be completely unchanged and
is going to be completely unchanged and
it doesn't end with sensuality. Like
that that whole
energy, let's say that you're building
up through those actions, that
translates to all the hindrances.
So like somebody who who has been
uh
seeking this engagement with sensual
objects is to that same extent going to
be even less able to put up with
uh the discomfort of things not going
their way.
More prone to aversion. Uh laziness.
Uh laziness.
Restlessness, doubts.
Cuz it's the same principle. Like
something unpleasant comes up
and you just have to act out of it. You
have to because that's the principle of
craving in general, like how it
provides some sort of uh relief to give
into it.
It's like two completely separate
things. The discomfort that you feel
The discomfort that you feel
and then the sort of activity
that you engage in that makes you not
have to look at it.
So it's it's it's like that's why in
fact the Buddha said one of the the
fundamental defilements as of us is
ignorance. It's not in some some mystical
It's not in some some mystical
uh uh cosmic lack of knowledge.
It's that same sort of
you could almost say like a belief or
view that uh that uh
engagement
functions as as solution from pain.
Which doesn't mean like you won't do
anything if you understand that.
Cuz the problem isn't action either.
It's action done specifically with that
purpose of covering up
that discomfort underneath, which is
what actually makes it hurt. The fact
that you're trying to to mask it
whichever means necessary rather than
than understanding this is what
existence is.
And then you will have absolutely no
need to
seek pleasant objects, which is really
what sensuality is, not whether they are
they are in the world.
>> So the the theme of
not distracting yourself
could actually be a theme that's
you can take from the courses to the
subtlest phenomena of existence. Like in the
phenomena of existence. Like in the
beginning you have the course versions,
but then actually distracting yourself
from basic facts of existence.
>> Yes, uh but you have to you have to
always keep it uh
organic. Like not kind of
abstractly thinking about oh,
distracting myself. I'm distracting
myself because
uh I'm deciding to
I don't know, read a book.
Which means I'm I'm I'm I'm trying to
escape from the raw discomfort of
existence. Well, are you? Like that's not
Well, are you? Like that's not
just something you decide
or or or or just that it's not something
that's inherent to the action.
Um you have to see is there something
unpleasant that I'm trying to run away
from? Like I actually have the view that
this will disappear.
This will be fixed. This discomfort will
be fixed if I read this book.
And that's when you're actually acting
out of hindrance.
>> And it would be completely fine
to read the book if it doesn't distract
me. >> Well, if it doesn't have that
>> Well, if it doesn't have that
implication
>> Mhm.
>> of a relief from this kind of pressure
then yes.
And then whatever you'll be reading the
book for wouldn't be
unwholesome. Uh so,
Uh so,
obviously, you know, it's it's not going
to be perfect in the beginning and you
might have
doubts and be reading books about the
Dhamma and stuff to kind of deal with
all of it, but um
it's certainly something you should uh
start to discern as
being rooted in your intentions as as we
always say.
So, that eventually you realize it's not
even just
in the same way as as uh with
sensuality, like um
it always depends on your intentions.
Uh there are certain things that are
always wrong, but fundamentally it
depends on your intentions.
Well, in the same way, it's not that
you're automatically justified in, for
example, reading about the Dhamma
because it's the Dhamma.
If it's coming out of that similar
compulsion that like this engagement
will mask the pain
that just pain of of
your mind being wound up with something.
Maybe not even related necessarily.
Uh then you have to see, wait, this is
unwholesome as well, then.
Regardless of the content.